Good morning. Today is April 3rd, April 4th, Monday. I'm Dan Margulies
filling in for Abba Windzer. It's the 25th of second אדר, Adar,
coming up on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan on Friday. No,
שבת. Shabbat. Okay, and we have to pick up on the bottom
of כ"ג עמוד א' Kaf Gimmel Amud Aleph 23a, in the middle
of the discussion about עבד כנעני, Eved Kenaani, this is slaves and
how are slaves acquired and how do slaves acquire their freedom. In
the משנה Mishnah there was a מחלוקת machlokes between חכמים Hakhamim and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir about whether the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says,
it's important to keep track of some of the details. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that how can a slave acquire his freedom? קונה
את עצמו בכסף על ידי אחרים, koneh et atzmo bakesef al yedei
acherim, other people can buy his freedom, ובשטר על ידי עצמו uvishtar
al yedei atzmo or he could receive a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
a freeing, not a divorce, a freeing freedom document from the slave
master. וחכמים אומרים בכסף על ידי עצמו, ve-Hakhamim omrim bakesef al yedei
atzmo, חכמים Hakhamim disagree, it seems, and say he could pay his
own freedom. However, ובשטר על ידי אחרים, uvishtar al yedei acherim, he
could only receive the שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for his freedom through
another person. And there was a bit of שקלא וטריא shakla ve-tarya
on כ"ג עמוד א' Kaf Gimmel Amud Aleph that suggests perhaps there's
a third opinion of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
in the משנה Mishnah as well. That is, חכמים Hakhamim actually think
that whether by money or by a שטר, shtar, the עבד eved
can acquire his own freedom, but רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar is the one who says that receiving the שטר shtar
must be על ידי אחרים. al yedei acherim. So now we start
the last two words on כ"ג עמוד א': Kaf Gimmel Amud Aleph:
בעי רבא לרבי שמעון בן אלעזר. bayei Rava le-Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
So רבא Rava asks a question on רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar.
We don't know the concept that גיטו וידו באים כאחד? gito veyado
ba'im ke'echad?
Right, it seems like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
opinion is that we would not hold by גיטו וידו באים כאחד,
gito veyado ba'im ke'echad, which was in general a principle we saw
throughout מסכת גיטין Masechet Gittin and was crucial to understanding how divorce
works and how freedom of a slave works. So the fact that
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar opinion pops up here
is important to note as well as it's important to note the
general principle that even in learning הלכות halakhot that are mostly found
in one מסכת, masechet, often there'll be little pieces here and there
across other מסכתות masekhtot and that's why we have ראשונים rishonim and
אחרונים acharonim to point us to the fact that we have to
keep our eyes open and they connect the dots for us. So
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar: so רבא Rava asks
a question on רבי שמעון בן אלעזר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar: עבד
כנעני מהו שיעשה שליח לקבל גיטו מיד רבו? eved kenaani ma hu
sheyaseh shaliach lekabel gito miyad rabo? Can an עבד כנעני eved kenaani
make a שליח shaliach to receive his גט get from his master?
כיוון דגמר לה לה מאישה, keivan degamar la-la me-ishah, because we learn
the freedom of עבד כנעני eved kenaani by a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah of the word לה la from divorce: כאישה, ke-ishah, that is
he could be compared to a woman who does have the power
to make a שליח shaliach to receive her divorce גט. get. או
דילמא אישה דאיהי מצי מקבלה גיטה שליח נמי מצי משוי: o dilma
ishah de'ihi matzi mekabel giteh shaliach nami matzi mashvei: so or would
we distinguish and say a woman who has the power to receive
her own גט, get, שליח נמי מצי משוי, shaliach nami matzi mashvei,
so too she has the power to make a שליח. shaliach. עבד
דאיהו לא מקבל גיטה: eved de'ihu lo mekabel giteh: but a slave
who does not have the power according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar to receive his own גט, get, שליח נמי
לא מצי משוי, shaliach nami lo matzi mashvei, and he would therefore
be unable to make a שליח shaliach to receive his own גט
get as well. That is רבא's Rava question, the assumption being that
this is an absurd position to take. That is obviously a slave
should be able to make a שליח shaliach to receive
his גט get too, I would think, I think it's package deal
personally.
Well, we're going to see. So בתר דבעי הדר פשטה: batar de-bayei
hadar pashatei: so רבא Rava answers his own question: לה לה מאישה,
la-la me-ishah, כאישה, ke-ishah, so we do learn the גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah לה לה la-la from אישה ishah and therefore slave being freed
is compared to a divorce, that is that it's derived from divorce.
ואלא הא דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: ve-ella had de-amar Rav
Huna berei de-Rav Yehoshua: and this is like the מחלוקת machlokes that
we saw or the question we saw in מסכת נדרים, Masechet Nedarim,
that is from רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: Rav Huna berei de-Rav
Yehoshua: הני כהני שלוחי דרחמנא נינהו? hani kohanei shluchei de-rachmana ninhu? Are
the כהנים kohanim שלוחי דרחמנא, shluchei de-rachmana ninhu, are they the representatives
of the תורה, Torah, the representatives of God, when they do the
עבודה? avodah? דאי סלקא דעתך שלוחי דידן נינהו: de'isalka da'atach shluchei didan
ninhu: if we would think that the כהנים kohanim are our שלוחי,
shluchei, that is if a person comes and brings a קרבן, korban,
מי איכא מידי דאנן לא מצנינן עבדינן ואיהו מצי עביד? mi ika
midi de'anan lo matzinan avdinan ve'ihu matzi avid? Are there שלוחי, shluchei,
can a שליח shaliach ever do something that the person, the משלח,
meshale'ach, who empowers the שליח shaliach is unable to do him or
herself? So that is false, right? We know that general principle from
מסכת נזיר Masechet Nazir דף י"ב: daf yud bet: the principle that
a שליח shaliach is only able to be created to do something
that you have the power to do yourself. So obviously the כהנים,
kohanim, since כהנים... kohanim... כהנים Kohanim can do the עבודה, avoda, but
a ישראל Yisrael cannot do the עבודה, avoda, it must be that
the כהנים Kohanim are not the שלוחים shlichim of בני ישראל, Bnei
Yisrael, they must be God's שלוחים. shlichim. Now obviously all of the
layers of meaning that's built upon this סוגיא sugya is of major
importance to understand קדשים. Kodshim.
Does it have any practical application or is it just theoretical?
Well nowadays it certainly doesn't have practical application.
But you were saying?
Meaning like we say, who is the... Correct. So the נפקא מינא
nafka mina in מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim was the question of if
you're מודר הנאה. mudar hana'ah. If you're מודר הנאה mudar hana'ah from
a כהן, Kohen, the נפקא מינא nafka mina is whether that כהן
Kohen could do עבודה avoda for you or not. So that is
a question of whether he is your שליח shaliach or whether he's
just doing the עבודה avoda for God and he happens to be
doing your קרבן korban today.
And the נפקא מינא nafka mina is how we think theologically
as well as practical.
Okay, there's a lot of material to cover today, we're going to
have to keep going. That's okay. Okay, מצי עביד ליה איהו מצי
מקבל גיטא שליח מצי משוי ולא איהו. matzi avid lei ihu matzi
mekabel gita shaliach matzi mishavei v'lo ihu. ישראל לא שייכי בתורת קרבנות
כלל. Yisrael lo shaychei b'torat korbanot klal. No,
the distinction between this סוגיא sugya and the סוגיא sugya in נדרים
Nedarim is like this. A ישראל Yisrael doesn't have any connection to
קרבנות, korbanot, meaning the עבודה avoda in general must be done totally
by כהנים Kohanim and therefore ישראל Yisrael is totally excluded. However, עבד
שייך בגיטין. eved shayach begittin. And an עבד, eved, a slave, is
fully connected to the notion of his bill of freedom. דתניא, detanya,
נירין הדברים שהעבד מקבל גיטו של חבירו מיד רבו של חבירו. nirin
hadevarim she'ha'eved mekabel gito shel chaveiro miyad rabo shel chaveiro. A slave
could receive his slave friend's freedom שטר, shtar, his גט שחרור get
shichrur from that slave's master. That is, he could himself be made
שליח shaliach for his friend to receive the גט. get. However, אבל
לא מיד רבו שלו. aval lo miyad rabo shelo. The problem is
not a problem that the עבד eved is unable to receive a
גט שחרור. get shichrur. The problem is that כל מה שקנה עבד
קנה רבו. kol ma shekana eved kana rabo. And therefore whatever the
slave acquires, the master himself acquires. Therefore a slave cannot receive his
own גט שחרור get shichrur into his own hand because it would
be like the master giving it back to himself. And therefore the
slave would never really receive
the גט get וגיטו וידו באין כאחד. v'gito v'yado ba'in k'echad.
So that's exactly the question and that's the point is that according
to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar who does not
hold by the principle of גיטו וידו באין כאחד, gito v'yado ba'in
k'echad, that's why he would think that the slave cannot accept his
own גט שחרור get shichrur and that is why רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar opinion is particularly interesting.
No, no, I got that. But he said נירין הדברים, nirin hadevarim,
which seems like he's saying that according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar or just saying that...
No, meaning that ברייתא braita sounds like it is according to רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar opinion. That ברייתא braita doesn't
talk about הלכה. halacha. Correct. It seems like the הלכה halacha would
be like חכמים Chachamim without any other clarification. I feel like that's
how it should go.
Also maybe if it says נירין הדברים, nirin hadevarim, so that sounds
like then yeah, this ברייתא, braita, this anonymous ברייתא braita supports רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. The הלכה halacha maybe should
be like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. That sounds
right. Okay, ובלבד שיהא הכסף משל אחרים. u'bilvad sheyehei hakesef mishel acheirim.
So that was now again going back, this סוגיא sugya is now
not going to be discussing רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar, this is going to take the original assumption of the משנה
Mishna that the משנה Mishna was just מחלוקת machloket between רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and חכמים. Chachamim. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that the
slave can acquire his own freedom, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says בכסף
על ידי אחרים ובשטר על ידי עצמו. bekessef al yedei acheirim u'veshtar
al yedei atzmo.
So other people can buy his freedom. And חכמים Chachamim say בכסף
על ידי עצמו, bekessef al yedei atzmo, however they say ובלבד שיהא
הכסף משל אחרים. u'bilvad sheyehei hakesef mishel acheirim.
So even though he can receive the money himself, like he can
hand the money to the בעל, ba'al, but the money must belong
to other people. So that's kind of a strange opinion. What does
that mean for חכמים? Chachamim? So חכמים Chachamim say ובלבד שיהא הכסף
משל אחרים. u'bilvad sheyehei hakesef mishel acheirim. נימא בהא קמיפלגי דרבי מאיר
סבר אין קניין לעבד בלא רבו. neima b'ha kamiflagi d'Rabbi Meir savar
ein kinyan l'eved belo rabo. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks that a
slave cannot acquire anything for himself without the master's consent, and if
it were with the master's consent then he's acquiring it for the
master anyway. ואין קניין לאישה בלא בעלה, ve'ein kinyan l'isha belo ba'ala,
and a woman the same thing, that whatever a woman is acquiring
goes to her husband. And therefore if she...
if someone were to try to transfer something to the woman by
herself it wouldn't work. ורבנן סברי יש קניין לעבד בלא רבו. veRabbanan
savrei yesh kinyan l'eved belo rabo.
The רבנן, Rabbanan, the חכמים Chachamim think that the slave can acquire
something without the master, and therefore the slave himself would have an
ability to have money of himself. But that's why the משנה Mishna
has to come and say ובלבד שיהא הכסף משל אחרים. u'bilvad sheyehei
hakesef mishel acheirim. ויש קניין לאישה בלא בעלה. ve'yesh kinyan l'isha belo
ba'ala. And a woman can acquire something without her husband. Okay, אמר
רבה בר רב ששת אמר רב ששת, amar Rabba bar Rav Sheshet
amar Rav Sheshet, לכולי עלמא אין קניין לעבד בלא רבו. le-kulei alma
ein kinyan l'eved belo rabo. No,
let's not read it that way. Let's assume everyone considers אין קניין
לעבד בלא רבו, ein kinyan l'eved belo rabo, that is a slave
cannot acquire anything without the master, ואין קניין לאישה בלא בעלה, ve-ein
kinyan l'isha belo ba'ala, and a woman cannot acquire anything without it
transferring to her husband.
They can make a deal not to, right?
Ah, so we're going to see. והכא במאי עסקינן דאקני ליה אחר
מנה ואמר לו על מנת שאין לרבך רשות בו. ve-hacha be-mai askinan
de-akni lei acher maneh ve-amar lo al menat she'ein lerabcha reshut bo.
What if someone goes to the slave and says here's a hundred
dollar bill on the condition that your master does not have rights
to it? That is, you only acquire it if the master does
not. And therefore he's trying to circumvent כל מה שקנה עבד קנה
רבו. kol ma shekana eved kana rabo. So he says, so that's
the מחלוקת, machloket, that's the מחלוקת machloket between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and חכמים. Chachamim. רבי מאיר סבר כי אמר ליה קני קני עבד
וקני רבו. Rabbi Meir savar ki amar lei kani kani eved v'kani
rabo.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks when he says acquire it, the
slave acquires it and therefore the master acquires it. וכי אמר ליה
על מנת לא כלום קאמר ליה.
v'chi amar lei al menat lo klum
ka'amar lei. And the trying to make this condition על מנת al
menat doesn't work.
It has no legal force.
Has no force because you're trying to undermine the basic notion of
what slavery is about, which is that you don't have your own
legal standing.
And this is עבד כנעני, eved K'naani, right? This is עבד כנעני
eved K'naani correct.
עבד עברי eved Ivri is a full standing Jewish Jewish man. הרבנן
סברי כיון דאמר ליה על מנת אהני ליה תנאי. ha-rabbanan savri keivan
d'amar lei al menat ahanei lei t'nai.
And the רבנן rabbanan think that this condition, this על מנת al
menat condition does work and so when he says על מנת al
menat it would work. ורבי אלעזר אמר כל כי האי גוונא לכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דקני עבד וקני רבו. v'Rabbi Elazar amar kol ki
hai gavna l'chulei alma lo pligi d'kani eved v'kani rabo. No,
nobody disagrees that when the slave acquires it, the master acquires it.
והכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאקני ליה אחר מנה ואמר ליה על מנת
שתצא בו לחירות. v'hacha b'mai askinan k'gon d'aknei lei acher maneh v'amar
lei al menat sheteitzei bo l'cheirut. No
it can't be that someone tried to give the slave the money
and then the slave took the money and tried to buy his
own freedom because everyone would agree when the slave tries to just
own a hundred dollars that it would go to the master. So
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says no no no, it must be in
one process. That is, someone goes up to the slave, gives him
the hundred dollar bill and says by me giving this to you,
now think about it, if it's כל מה שקנה עבד קנה רבו,
kol mah shekanah eved kanah rabo, so then it will be going
to the slave master. So he is trying to buy the slave's
freedom by giving a hundred dollars to the slave. So that's the
mechanism that's at play. רבי מאיר סבר כי אמר ליה קני קני
עבד וקני רבו. Rabbi Meir savar ki amar lei kani kani eved
v'kani rabo. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks that that would work.
וכי אמר ליה על מנת לא כלום קאמר ליה v'chi amar lei
al menat lo klum ka'amar lei but when he says על מנת,
al menat, the condition that it should be על מנת al menat
that you go free doesn't work. So it's just like giving a
hundred dollars to the slave master. They don't just get their money
back really because the only reason he's doing that was to...
well that's a question of the deal not going through. Right. But
the point is that what you tried to do didn't work. רבנן
סברי לדידיה נמי הא לא קא מקני ליה והא לא אמר ליה
אלא על מנת שתצא בו לחירות. rabbanan savri l'didei nami ha lo
ka maknei lei v'ha lo amar lei ela al menat sheteitzei bo
l'cheirut. The... so and
therefore the רבנן rabbanan's opinion is that when you say it like
this, רבנן סברי לדידיה נמי, rabbanan savri l'didei nami, so for him
also, meaning that it goes to him, that is that it would
work through that this condition would work and therefore that the slave
can go free because it's like giving it to the master. That
is, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and חכמים Chachamim both agree that it's
like giving it to the master. The question is whether by giving
money to the slave who then acquires it on the master's behalf,
does that work to free the slave or not? That's the question.
It's kind of the opposite, isn't it?
It's kind of the opposite. That is, he acquires his own freedom
precisely because right now he is not his own person. Right.
So let me just understand this. So basically this is only this
is the only way an עבד eved can quote unquote get money
according to both opinions?
Well and even there, according to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar he can't.
That is, an עבד eved has no ability to have private ownership
and that's different than a married woman. A married woman obviously is
allowed to have her own private assets that are reserved and set
aside separate from the principle of כל מה שקנתה אשה קנה בעלה
kol mah shekantah ishah kanah ba'alah which has more to do with
שעבודים shibudim and פירות peirot and not... so there are a lot
of layers of ownership in a marital relationship and shared bank account,
a separate bank account which we're going to get to right now,
the question of מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
And according to this, the עבד eved does not acquiring the money.
Right. That's what I'm saying.
Meaning like I was just saying, an עבד eved can't own anything
in and of itself according to... No, but according to the position
that עבד עברי גופו קנוי. eved Ivri gufo kanoo.
No, but עבד עברי, eved Ivri, the position about עבד עברי גופו
קנוי eved Ivri gufo kanoo is more about his marital relationship, is
about the relationship with a שפחה כנענית. shifchah K'naanit. It's much less
in any sense about the fact that the עבד עברי eved Ivri
loses his legal standing as an adult person.
If he's גופו קנוי gufo kanoo he still can't give him something,
it goes to his master. Of course, עבד עברי eved Ivri is
a person.
He doesn't have to consult. Correct.
There's no principle of כל מה שקנה עבד קנה רבו kol mah
shekanah eved kanah rabo by עבד עברי. eved Ivri. עבד עברי, eved
Ivri, that's the משנה mishnah in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, right? אלו
מציאות שלו. eilu metzios shelo. In the second פרק perek there's a
list of who are the people who who are... אלו מציאות. eilu
metzios.
No
not about the... no it's later in the second פרק perek but
so the list of בניו ובנותיו הגדולים banav uvnosav hagedolim and עבד
עברי eved Ivri and and and its אשתו
המגורשת ishto hagerushah or something like that. So a list of people
for whom they have their own ownership for מציאות metzios and that's
separate from people who are מארסת m'areset and...
no meaning עבד עברי eved Ivri no one thinks that עבד עברי
eved Ivri is קונה koneh for the master. The point is we're
talking about עבד כנעני. eved K'naani. It's a separate הלכה halachic point
and עבד עברי eved Ivri is an adult, is a human being
separate from an עבד כנעני. eved K'naani. עבד כנעני eved K'naani is
much more like...
thinking about a human being much more like property in the sense
of thinking about this person's much more like like livestock that is
owned by by the slave master. And that's why the the rights
that the master has to whatever this person does as a slave
is much closer to how you would imagine really a full extension
of the owner's of the owner's power. That's really what's deeply problematic
about slavery and that's why we don't do it anymore. Okay, the
last line of כג עמוד ב. Kaf Gimel Amud Bet. רמי דרבי
מאיר אדרבי מאיר רמי דרבנן אדרבנן, Rami de-Rabbi Meir a-de-Rabbi Meir, Rami
de-Rabbanan a-de-Rabbanan, דתניא. de-tanya. So
we have a ברייתא braita that's now going to contradict both רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir שיטה shita and רבנן's Rabbanan שיטה. shita. It sounds
like in this ברייתא braita they have the opposite opinion. So we're
going to see. אין אשה פודה מעשר שני בלא חומש. Ein ishah
podeh Maaser Sheni belo chomesh.
A woman cannot redeem מעשר שני Maaser Sheni without paying a חומש.
chomesh. That means what's the case? מעשר שני Maaser Sheni if you
were פודה podeh your own מעשר שני Maaser Sheni the Torah requires
that you pay חומש. chomesh. חומש chomesh being 25% extra, you pay
125% of the price of the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. No, חומש
chomesh is 1/5 of the final amount, so it's 25%. That's the
tricksy part.
So 25% and that's kind of like a fine on relying on
פדיון, pidyon, redeeming the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Normally you would want
to actually be able to schlepp all of your produce to ירושלים
Yerushalayim to eat it there. Those fruits have the קדושת מעשר שני
kedushat Maaser Sheni themselves. But if it's too far, too many fruits,
thank God you're so prosperous it's too hard to schlepp, so you
transfer the קדושת מעשר שני kedushat Maaser Sheni onto money and then
you add a חומש. chomesh. So you bring 125% of the value
of that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni produce, you go to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and you buy new fruits and eat it there. It's a מחלוקת
machloket between the רמב''ן Ramban and the רמב''ם Rambam in ספר המצוות
Sefer HaMitzvot about whether there is a מצוה mitzvah to eat מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni or not. The רמב''ם Rambam seems to think there's
no מצוה mitzvah specifically to eat the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. It's
more עשה הבא מכלל לאו. aseh ha-ba mikhlal lav. He thinks there
are prohibitions about not eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni but nothing about
actually a מצוה mitzvah to eat it, and the רמב''ן Ramban disagrees.
So אשה, ishah,
אין אשה פודה מעשר שני בלא חומש. ein ishah podeh Maaser Sheni
belo chomesh. That means if a woman is being פודה podeh her,
presumably the produce of her and her husband's field,
she's פודה podeh that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni fruit onto silver money,
so she does not get to exempt herself from the חומש. chomesh.
That means that she has to pay חומש. chomesh. That means it's
considered to be hers or that she's acting on her husband's behalf
as a שליח. shaliach. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Meir, not as a שליח.
shaliach. Sorry. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר אשה פודה
מעשר שני בלא חומש. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Meir,
ishah podeh Maaser Sheni belo chomesh. And רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir opinion
is that she could not pay the חומש. chomesh. That is, that
a woman is separate from her husband in this regard.
So היכי דמי? heichi dami? אי לימא בזוזי דבעל ומעשר דבעל, ei
leima be-zuzei de-ba'al u-ma'aser de-ba'al, maybe it's the husband's money and it's
the husband's fruits.
שליחותיה דבעל קעבדה. shelichutei de-ba'al ka-avdah. So then she's just doing the
שליחות shlichut of the husband and then she should have to pay
חומש. chomesh. ואלא בזוזי דידה ומעשר דידה, ve-ela be-zuzei didah u-ma'aser didah,
what if it's her money and the husband's fruits? איש אמר רחמנא
ולא אשה. ish amar Rachmana velo ishah. So it sounds like from
the Torah there's a special דרשה drasha to exclude a woman from
paying חומש. chomesh. This is a major מחלוקת machloket between רש''י Rashi
and תוספות. Tosafot. רש''י Rashi here and תוספות Tosafot towards the bottom
where it says הכי גרסינן. hachi garsinan. רש''י, Rashi, אלא בזוזי דידה
ובמעשר דידה. ela be-zuzei didah u-ve-ma'aser didah. And it has to do
with extensively about what is the exemption of a woman, a woman's
exemption from מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Is it a much more general
exemption? תוספות Tosafot seems to understand it's much more about the question
of how bringing מעשר שני Maaser Sheni to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eating
it there is connected to the מצוה mitzvah of תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah because the Torah talks about ולמדת. ve-lamadeta. Yeah, by מעשר שני.
Maaser Sheni.
So that seems to be the question there and there's extensive question
in תוספות, Tosafot, but part of that question has to do with
how intrinsic is the question of חומש chomesh to the question of
מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Obviously a woman has an obligation to separate
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim the same
as a man. The question is, is the חומש chomesh connected to
the taking of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in general? פודה מעשר שני
podeh Ma'aser Sheni is part of the מצוה mitzvah and adding a
חומש chomesh is just part of the פדיון? pidyon? Or is the
חומש chomesh some separate tax that's added on separately that could have
different rules? So, but תוספות Tosafot doesn't like רש''י's Rashi גירסא. girsa.
It's a bit complicated, but that's part of the question there. So
it says איש אמר רחמנא ולא אשה, ish amar Rachmana velo ishah,
אלא לאו כי האי גוונא דאקני לה אחר מנה ואמר לה על
מנת שתפדי בו את המעשר. ela lav ki hai gavna de-aknei lah
acher mane ve-amar lah al menat she-tifdi bo et ha-maaser. No, another
person came to this woman and gave her a piece of a
silver coin and said to her, use this money...
what was the question of איש ולא אשה? ish velo ishah?
Meaning that the woman herself is looking at what רש''י Rashi says,
איש אמר רחמנא ולא אשה, ish amar Rachmana velo ishah, איש ממעשרו
אמר רחמנא ולא אשה ממעשר בעלה דאשה כאחר דמיא. ish mi-maasero amar
Rachmana velo ishah mi-maaser baalah de-ishah ke-acher damya. A woman is considered
to be a separate person from her husband regarding מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni that she should not have to pay the חומש. chomesh.
Yes, so the question would be what? So that agrees with רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Yeah, that's the support for רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
I thought that was the question.
The question is, where are we talking? The question is that this
ברייתא Baraisa from תוספתא Tosefta in מעשר שני Maaser Sheni seems to
contradict the opinions we had lined up about עבד כנעני Eved K'naani
for עבד כנעני. Eved K'naani. That is, עבד כנעני Eved K'naani according
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks that the
slave
cannot even be given money on the condition that he frees himself
right now, and the חכמים Chachamim say that that would work. And
here, רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's opinion says what? We were just getting
to it. So, the whole point of ולא ישא אשה כי האי
גוונא, velo yisha isha ki hai gavna, what case are we talking
about? דאקני לאחר מנה ואמר לה על מנת שתפדי בו את המעשר.
d'aknei l'acher maneh v'amar la al m'nas she'tifdi bo es hama'aser. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir must be talking about a case where someone else
came to this woman, said here is this money to use for
פדיון מעשר שני pidyon Ma'aser Sheni because otherwise how could you have
a case where the woman is using money that does not belong
to her husband to be פודה podeh מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni that
does belong to her husband, therefore that she could avoid the חומש.
chomesh. So one answer then we have to say is, איפכא שמינא
להו. ipcha shamina lehu. We just heard it reversed. That is, one
of these two sources, probably the ברייתא, Baraisa, is reverse of חכמים'ס
Chachamim's opinion and רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position, and that way we
solve the contradiction. That is, רבנן Rabbanan will still say that it
works, giving someone something על מנת al m'nas that you use it
specifically for this purpose even when it's something that remains outside of
your ownership, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would disagree. But אמר אביי:
amar Abaye: איפוך. ipoch. So אביי Abaye says fine, it's reversed. רבא
אמר לעולם לא תיפוך. Rava amar l'olam lo sipoach. No, I don't
like switching around משניות Mishnayos and ברייתות Baraisos to just make it
fit. Obviously we have to understand what the מחלוקת machlokes is about.
And רבא Rava is going to introduce a distinction between מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni with a married woman and the freedom of a slave.
דהכא במעשר דאתיה מבי נשא עסקינן. dhacha b'ma'aser d'asya mibei nasha askinan.
No, we're talking about מעשר Ma'aser which she has inherited. That is,
this woman's father died and she has no brothers, so she inherits
the father's property including מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni fruits. And now what
is trying to, what's she trying to do? She wants the, so
the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni fruits totally belong to her. And that's
the point. And that's why there's this special exemption of a woman
to pay חומש chomesh separate from the fact that, so she must
be acting on her own accord for her own property, and nonetheless
she's exempted from the חומש. chomesh. רבי מאיר לטעמיה דאמר מעשר ממון
הקדש הוא. Rabbi Meir l'taimei d'amar Ma'aser mamon hekdesh hu. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir thinks that מעשר Ma'aser is owned by הקדש, hekdesh, that
is מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni really belongs to God. And this is
a fundamental מחלוקת. machlokes. ולא קני ליה בעל, velo kanei lei ba'al,
and the husband does not acquire it. ורבנן לטעמייהו דאמרי ממון הדיוט
הוא וקני ליה בעל. v'rabbanan l'taimaihu d'amri mamon hedyot hu v'kanei lei
ba'al. And the רבנן, Rabbanan, the חכמים Chachamim think that מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni actually belongs to the, is your own money, and therefore
the husband acquires it. הלכך שליחותא דבעל קא עבדה, hilcach shlichusa d'ba'al
q'avda, and then the woman is really just doing the שליחות shlichus
of her husband or not. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir thinks she's
doing it for herself because it really belongs to הקדש hekdesh and
it's her responsibility to deal with her own מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni,
and רבנן Rabbanan think that מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni is money and
transfers to the husband, and therefore she's doing it on her husband's
behalf, and that's why she would have to do the חומש. chomesh.
You don't need the inheritance case then. In other words, you have
a more fundamental מחלוקת machlokes as to whether or not the מעשר
שני Ma'aser Sheni belongs to הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu or
not, right? So, so even if it's the פירות peiros from the
בעל, ba'al, once it's מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni it's no longer his
and you could still argue that she could...
Ah, okay, so that's going to be a separate question. That is,
we can bifurcate, yes, it is clear, but we have to bifurcate
two different aspects of what's going on with מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
We have to talk about the monetary value and we have to
talk about the obligation intrinsic to the fruits of מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni to eat them in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So, and that's the way
many of the אחרונים Acharonim try to frame it, which is that
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni could be inherited. מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni you
can use
an אתרוג esrog of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni on סוכות. Sukkos. That
is, it can belong to you in a monetary sense, but at
some level it's still could be connected somehow still של גבוה. shel
gavo'ah. And obviously the way that מעשר Ma'aser is של גבוה shel
gavo'ah or של הקדש shel hekdesh is different than other kinds of
הקדש hekdesh in that what? מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni everyone is allowed
to eat it. You have to eat it בטהרה b'tahara in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, but even ישראלים Yisraelim can eat it. It's different than קרבנות
korbanos and things like that. You get a full, full definition of
the city of ירושלים Yerushalayim like certain kinds of קדשים. kodshim. It's
similar in some sense to the בכור bechor and מעשר בהמה. ma'aser
behemah. So מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah are similar
in many ways, but מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni at the same time
you could be פודה podeh and purchase other things. So it's a
more fluid kind of הקדש, hekdesh, but at its core somehow is
still an obligation coming from God. It's also interesting just to think
about who owns the fruits, right? Do you own the fruits and
you're giving them to God, you're bringing them to ירושלים Yerushalayim to
eat them with God, or really no? It really belongs to God
and you have to, in order to be allowed to eat it,
you have to go to ירושלים Yerushalayim because that's where it belongs.
So that's part of the question as well. תרומה Terumah is almost
the opposite. תרומה, Terumah, the fruit belongs to me and I have
to then transfer it to the כהן. Kohen. That's almost the opposite
of מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni where מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni the גמרא
Gemara is telling us belongs to God and I have to eat
it myself but in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's part of the interesting
and מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni again becomes a major test case for
all sorts of different kinds of things. It has monetary aspects, it
has קרבנות korbanot aspects, it has many different layers. Okay. תנא. Tana.
תניא דבי ש Tanya de-Vei She so we have a now a
ברייתא braita talking about how else can an עבד כנעני Eved Kena'ani
go free? Interesting question just to think about why are these listed
here and not in the משנה? Mishna? So תנא, Tana, יוצא בשן
ועין. Yotzei beshein ve'ayin. A slave goes free if the master knocks
out his tooth or his eye וראשי אברים שאינן חוזרין u-roshei evarim
she-einan chozrin and the tips of limbs that do not grow back.
There are 24 limbs that have that their tip. This is also
the place where you can't get צרעת tzara'at because you can't see
it from all sides if it's at the tip you have to
look at it from different angles in order to see it all
at once. That's the idea. So by נגעים nega'im the tips of
the limbs also have a special significance. So here too with a
slave going free. So תנא, Tana, יוצא בשן ועין וראשי אברים שאינן
חוזרין, Yotzei beshein ve'ayin u-roshei evarim she-einan chozrin, the tips of the
limbs that do not grow back. בשלמא שן ועין כתיבי. Bishlama shein
ve'ayin ketivei. So a tooth and an eye are mentioned explicitly in
the תורה. Torah. So that's why he should go free. אלא ראשי
אברים מנלן? Ela roshei evarim minalan? How do I know also from
the tips of limbs? So דומיא דשן ועין. dumya de-shein ve'ayin. It's
because they're similar to the tooth and the eye. מה שן ועין
מום שבגלוי ואינן חוזרין, Ma shein ve'ayin mum she-bagalui ve-einan chozrin, just
like the tooth and the eye are visible blemishes, that is they
are on parts of the body that are exposed, ואינן חוזרין ve-einan
chozrin and they don't grow back, אף כל מום שבגלוי ואינן חוזרין.
af kol mum she-bagalui ve-einan chozrin. So any kind of defect, any
kind of injury to the body that is visible and does not
grow back. It doesn't have to be just the tips of the
limbs maybe? ואימא מנהוי שן ועין כשני כתובים הבאים כאחד Ve-eima minahavei
shein ve'ayin ki-shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad and maybe since שן shein and
עין ayin are both mentioned explicitly, that becomes like a בנין אב
משני כתובים. binyan av mi-shnei ketuvim. There are two references to specific
exceptions and therefore because they are two exceptions we can't build a
general case from it. וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. Ve-chol
shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad ein melamdin. This is actually מחלוקת תנאים machloket
tannaim we're going to see in the towards the end of the
first פרק. perek. But וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. ve-chol
shnei ketuvim ha-ba'im ke-echad ein melamdin. If there are two examples of
something we can't make a generalization unless we need each of them.
צריכא דאיכתבא רחמנא שן הוה אמינא אפילו שן
דחלב.
Tzricha de-iktava rachmana shein hava amina
afilu shein de-chalav. If it had just said tooth I would have
thought even a milk tooth, milk tooth that is what we call
a baby tooth. Okay. רש"י Rashi says שן שינק בה, shein she-yanak
bah, a tooth that grows in while you're still nursing. Interesting also
to note the fact that maybe we often wean children off of
breastfeeding earlier than in the times of חז"ל. Chazal. Perhaps not, I
don't know, different families do different things. כתב רחמנא עין. Katav rachmana
ayin. That's why the תורה Torah includes the eye as well. ואי
כתב רחמנא עין הוה אמינא מה עין נברא עמו, Ve-iy katav rachmana
ayin hava amina ma ayin nivra imo, the
eye is created with you, אף כל שנברא עמו אבל שן לא,
af kol she-nivra imo aval shein lo, so then everything that is
created with you but not the tooth because the teeth grow in
later. צריכא. Tzricha. And that's why we need both. Interesting the גמרא
Gemara in נדה Niddah in the list of all the different parts
of the body that the different parents and God contribute to the
growing fetus and when a child is born, so the teeth are
mentioned as part of the white parts of the body like the
white of the eye, the bones and things like that, the teeth
are also mentioned. So it's interesting to consider do we think the
teeth grow in after the child is born or the teeth, you
know again medically also the question about permanent teeth and when they
form and all sorts of interesting things.
And hair also?
And hair also grows in later. Well also hair is not meaning
I cut your hair there's no permanent damage by any
means. Okay. ואימא כי יכה כלל. Ve-eima ki yakkeh klal. So maybe
we should read the פסוק pasuk like this to try to see
כלל ופרט. klal u-prat. It says כי יכה, ki yakkeh, if you
strike, so that's a general mention. שן ועין פרט, Shein ve-ayin prat,
and then the mention of the tooth and the eye are specific.
כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. Klal u-prat ein ba-klal ela
mah she-ba-prat.
And therefore you should not go free except for tooth and eye
because the פרט prat comes to limit the כלל. klal. Okay. שן
ועין אין מידי אחרינא לא. Shein ve-ayin in midei achrina lo.
So for no other limb should he go free. לחפשי ישלחנו. Le-chofshi
yeshalchenu. So the end of the פסוק pasuk says you have to
send him free. חוזר וכלל. Chozer ve-klal.
No, the end goes free when he goes free so that tells
you that it's a more general notion, כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat
u-klal. And the fact of כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal then
the generality at the end comes to expand the notion of the
specifics in the middle. אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. Ei ata
dan ela ke-ein ha-prat. So then you follow the פרט. prat. You
have to make it general but it has to follow the rules
of the פרט. prat. מה הפרט מפורש מום שבגלוי ואינן חוזרין. Mah
ha-prat meforash mum she-bagalui ve-einan chozrin. So just like it is a
visible blemish that does not grow
back, אף כל מום שבגלוי af kol mum she-bagalui
No, the Torah is specific, it's not just that it doesn't grow
back. Also that it's בטל ממלאכתו, batel m'melachto, that the knocking out
of a tooth or knocking out of an eye actually cancels out
the ability of that limb to do its normal function ואינו חוזר
v'eino chozer and it doesn't grow back. אף כל מומים שבגלוי, af
kol mumim shebagalui, if it's visible ואינו חוזר v'eino chozer does not
grow back ובטל ממלאכתו u'batel m'melachto and it cannot do its normal
function. אלמא תניא, alma tanya, it's like this ברייתא: braisa: תלש בזקנו,
talash b'zikano, what if the slave master came and pulled on his
beard ודלדל בו עצם v'dildel bo etzem
and it therefore, by pulling on the beard, it dislocated the slave's
jaw? That is, his jawbone was dislocated. Okay,
so עבד יוצא בהם לחירות. eved yotzei bahem l'cheirus. So then the
slave goes free because of that too. That means that because he
won't be able to eat properly anymore, to chew properly, that's also
considered to be its מומים שבגלוי mumim shebagalui because you could notice
when someone's jaw is dislocated. It's not חוזר, chozer, the jaw cannot
go back in on its own, and it's ובטל ממלאכתו u'batel m'melachto
because you can't eat properly anymore.
So you're saying it has to be able to go back on
its own?
Well, חוזר, chozer, what does חוזר chozer mean? It heals. It's some
kind of injury that heals,
with medical.
Right, so they didn't have that medical. Presumably,
and that's an interesting question. If there were slaves now, but we
also had medical, modern medicine, how much would we consider the ability
to even, you know, repair a lost tooth or to reinsert the
tooth or to have a false tooth, or attach a hand, right,
attach a finger?
Do they heal like broken arms?
Broken arm, I feel like they had some knowledge of setting the
bone, but for the jaw, maybe it was different, even if it
would set, it wouldn't set properly. I'm not 100% sure about that,
but that's the suggestion here, at least from that ברייתא, braisa, that
dislocated jaw, maybe it's not exactly about the dislocation, maybe it's something
else. Not 100% sure. Okay, so ולחפשי ישלחנו, u'l'chofshi yishalchenu, so he
has to send him free. ריבויה הוא. ribuyo hu. ואי ריבויה הוא,
v'ee ribuyo hu, אפילו הכהו על ידו afilu hikahu al yado וצמתה
ולסוף חזרה. v'tzamta u'lesof chazra.
So if it's a ריבוי, ribui, if it's a very general notion,
so then it should even include if he punched the slave on
the arm and his arm withered or the arm got very damaged
וסוף חזרה, v'sof chazra, in the end it healed after a long
time. So נמי אמר תניא, nami amar tanya, הכהו על ידו וצמתה
ולסוף חזרה, hikahu al yado v'tzamta u'lesof chazra, אין עבד יוצא בו
לחירות. ein eved yotzei bo l'cheirus. And that's why the ברייתא braisa
has to mention explicitly that if he punches him in the arm
and the arm goes dead for a long time but eventually heals
again, then that would not be a reason for the slave to
go free. So that concrete example, that statement teaches us how to
limit the hermeneutic application of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u'prat u'klal. Right.
Exactly. And that's exactly a point that the notion of חוזר chozer
or אינו חוזר eino chozer becomes an important qualification here. So אם
כן, im kein, שן ועין, shen v'ayin, מאי אהני ליה? mai ahani
leh? So then why should the tooth and the
eye be the examples given? דתנו רבנן, d'tanu rabanan, בכולם עבד יוצא
בהם לחירות. b'chulam eved yotzei bahem l'cheirus. For all of these, the
slave goes free. So what's the difference? וצריך גט שחרור, v'tzarich get
shichrur, דברי רבי שמעון. divrei Rabi Shimon.
So according to רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon, for injuring any of these
limbs, the slave needs a גט שחרור. get shichrur. That is, it
creates an obligation for the master to free the slave by a
normal mechanism. It's not a way for the slave to go free.
רבי מאיר אומר, Rabi Meir omer, אינו צריך. eino tzarich. רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir thinks the injury to the slave is itself a mechanism
for the slave to go free. רבי אליעזר אומר צריך, Rabi Eliezer
omer tzarich, and רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer agrees with רבי שמעון. Rabi
Shimon. רבי טרפון אומר אינו צריך. Rabi Tarfon omer eino tzarich. רבי
טרפון Rabi Tarfon agrees with רבי מאיר. Rabi Meir. רבי עקיבא אומר
צריך. Rabi Akiva omer tzarich. And רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva agrees with
רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon and רבי אליעזר. Rabi Eliezer. So המכריעים לפני
חכמים אומרים, hamachri'im lifnei chachamim omrim, נראין דברי רבי טרפון בשן ועין.
nir'in divrei Rabi Tarfon b'shen v'ayin. So they agree with רבי טרפון
Rabi Tarfon and רבי מאיר Rabi Meir in a case of שן
ועין shen v'ayin which are mentioned explicitly in the Torah, שהתורה זכתה
לו, shehatorah zach'ta lo, because the Torah itself mentioned them explicitly, so
the mechanism is somehow already at play. Now again, this goes back
to the discussion in the גמרא Gemara in סוטה Sotah that talked
about how... never mind, too far afield. Okay, שהתורה זכתה לו, shehatorah
zach'ta lo, ודברי רבי עקיבא בשאר איברים. v'divrei Rabi Akiva b'sha'ar eivarim.
And רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva by other limbs, that is injury to
the tip of the finger or something like that, that he would
still it would create an obligation on the master to write a
גט שחרור get shichrur for the slave. הואיל... ho'il... yeah, who are
המכריעים? hamachri'im? The המכריעים, hamachri'im, that is, when this מחלוקת machlokes came
before a more general group of חכמים, chachamim, and they had to
decide how the הלכה halacha should be, they adopted a compromise position.
They said רבי טרפון Rabi Tarfon makes sense for שן ועין, shen
v'ayin, and רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva makes sense for other limbs, and
we're going to see why, הואיל וקנס חכמים הוא, ho'il u'knas chachamim
hu, because it's actually only rabbinic. קנס הוא? knas hu? קראי קדרשינן!
krai k'darshinan! What do you mean, it's rabbinic? It's derived from verses!
Whoever said that the other limbs are Rabbinic? We learn them from
כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u'prat u'klal. כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal
is a דרשה drasha on a פסוק. pasuk. So how can you
say that that's only a Rabbinic mechanism? Okay. אלא הואיל ומדרש חכמים
הוא, Ella ho'il u'midrash chachamim hu, because it's a מדרש חכמים, midrash
chachamim, it's not explicit in the פסוק pasuk and we see especially
the Rambam distinguishes between things which are learned out from דרשות drashot
and things which are explicit in the פסוקים psukim that those even
if they carry what we what we would call דאורייתא d'oraita weight,
things are learned from דרשות drashot have somehow lesser halakhic weight than
things which are explicit in the Torah. This is a fascinating statement.
Lesser halakhic weight meaning not דאורייתא? d'oraita? Meaning so not what the
Rambam would call דאורייתא. d'oraita. We would call it דאורייתא. d'oraita. So
he would say דאורייתא d'oraita is so to speak explicit in the
פסוקים psukim vs. על ידי דרשה. al yedei drasha. And that's a
מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
I forget where now, about whether the majority of the Torah is
תורה שבכתב Torah she'bichsav or the majority is תורה שבעל פה. Torah
she'ba'al peh. How could they have such a מחלוקת? machloket? Whether they
count things learned from דרשות drashot as תורה שבעל פה Torah she'ba'al
peh or תורה שבכתב. Torah she'bichsav. So if if תורה שבכתב Torah
she'bichsav means it's really is connected to the פסוקים, psukim, it really
is buried inside the the written Torah, and the fact that חז"ל
Chazal had to use דרשות drashot to extract it just means that
they're uncovering something that was hidden. But if you want to say
that the majority is תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'ba'al peh, then even
דרשות drashot which are based on פסוקים psukim are not really in
the פסוקים, psukim, they're sort of somehow really were an oral tradition
or oral הלכות halachot or legislation that was then connected to the
פסוקים psukim afterwards. Okay. So מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Shimon? How can רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon have this opinion? So יליף
שילוח שילוח מאישה. yalif shiluach shiluach m'isha. He learns the freeing of
a slave from a woman who gets divorced. מה אישה בשטר אף
עבד נמי בשטר. Mah isha b'shtar af eved nami b'shtar. Because a
woman is divorced by by a גט, get, so too a slave
has to go free with with a גט שטר שחרור. get shtar
shichrur. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אי כתב חופשי לבסוף כדקאמר השתא דכתיב
לחופשי ישלחנו. ei katav chofshi l'bisof k'd'ka'amar hashta d'chtiv lachofshi yishalchenu. The
פסוק pasuk says לחופשי ישלחנו, lachofshi yishalchenu, you have to send him
free. הוה ליה חופשי מעיקרא. hava lei chofshi me'ikara. He's actually already
free, meaning that at the time of the injury, not there's a
מצוה mitzvah to free him, but that he actually already went free.
גיטו בידו? Gitto b'yado? Almost well it's interesting it's not even גיטו
בידו, gitto b'yado, right? You punch him in the eye or something,
he becomes free. Right. In that sec- so that's really a question
about what is this guarantee on the slave's well-being. This is about
not this is really a disincentive to the slave master to injure
a slave. The question is is it what kind of a disincentive
is it? If it were just a disincentive then it would be
fine to hold like like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that is, it
creates an obligation to free the slave normally. But according to רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir position, a maltreated slave actually you the the master
has undermined the halakhic responsibility that he has as a slave master
and totally falls out of the picture. It's almost like it's not
that the slave is going free, it's that the master loses his
slave masterness. And therefore without an אדון, adon, the slave becomes free
automatically almost, because he violated the responsibilities. Still masters others? Right, but
the point is that for this the relationship with this slave under-
it's it's almost out of the right. It's like the difference between
divorce and and the death of the husband. The death of the
husband sort of the husband is is leaving the picture, and with
divorce it's the wife who's being divorced. So really different mechanisms about
ending marriage as well. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: הכהו על עינו וסמאה.
hikeihu al eino v'sima'ah. What if he hit him on his eye
and the eye went blind? That is, not that the eye was
physically damaged, but that the eye loses its ability to see. על
אזנו וחרשה, al ozno v'chershah, or if he hit him on the
ear and he went deaf in that ear, עבד יוצא בהן לחירות.
eved yotzei bahen l'cheirus. And then the slave goes free from those
kinds of injuries. That is, that becoming blind or becoming deaf in
that ear or that eye is enough of an injury to that
limb to be considered that that it was damaged in that way.
Who pays for the injury? What kind of an injury? Who pays
for the injury? Well, the slave goes free because of it. So
in a sense that is enough. But if he wasn't good he
goes free? Does that work? Well, but now what you he can
still see in one eye or something like that? So doesn't the
master then have to pay? No, the the master does not have
to pay any other damages. That is because the slave buys his
own freedom through this injury. It is a good question, it's a
very good question actually. It's interesting what if the injury to the
slave were somehow worth more than his slave value? I think in
general a slave's value probably would be much higher than any individual
injury. But it's interesting question. It doesn't really only necessarily because we
said that like the fact that he's getting if it was a
good worker right? The question of is it זכות zechus or חוב.
chov. Right, so like I- Okay, so כנגד עינו ואינו רואה, keneged
eino v'eino ro'eh, כנגד אזנו ואינו שומע. keneged ozno v'eino shomei'a. אין
עבד יוצא בהן לחירות *ein eved yotzei bahen lecherut*. So what if
you didn't punch him in the eye? What if you somehow made
something happen right in front of his eye so that he lost
his sight? And it's interesting, it doesn't say וסמאה *usam'ah*, made the
eye blind, but אינו רואה *eino ro'eh*, he cannot see. Interesting how
the injury is framed differently, but somehow a non-contact injury that results
in the slave either losing his ability to see through that eye
or losing his ability to hear through that ear, but non-contact injury,
אין עבד יוצא בהן לחירות *ein eved yotzei bahen lecherut*, the slave
does not go free. אמר רב שמן לרב אשי *amar Rav Shemen
le-Rav Ashi*, למימרא דקלא לאו כלום הוא *lememra dekala lav klum hu*,
that's to tell you that קול *kol*, that is a sound, does
not have a physical form. והתני *ve-hatani*, but isn't there this ברייתא
*braita* that came up in בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*? זו רמי בר
יחזקאל *zu Rami bar Yechezkel*, תרנגול שהושיט ראשו לאויר כלי זכוכית ותקע
vetaka בו ושברו משלם נזק שלם *tarnegol shehoshit rosho la'avir kli zechuchit
vetaka bo veshivaro meshalem nezek shalem*. If a chicken puts its head
inside of a glass vessel and crows inside the glass and the
glass breaks—this is a Talmudic approach to the opera, the fat lady
sings—so the chicken puts its head inside the glass and crows and
the glass breaks, but the chicken did not contact the glass in
any way. According to סומכוס׳ס *Sumchos's* view, משלם נזק שלם *meshalem nezek
shalem*, he pays full נזק *nezek*. ואמר רב יוסף אמר בי רב
*ve'amar Rav Yosef amar bei Rav*, סוס שצנף וחמור שנער ושברו כלים
בתוך הבית משלמין חצי נזק *sus shetzanaf vechamor shenaar veshavru kelim betoch
habayit meshalmin chatzi nezek*. And the opinion from בי רב *bei Rav*
that if a horse whinnies and a donkey brays and they broke
כלים *kelim* that are in the house, they pay חצי נזק *chatzi
nezek*. You pay half נזק *nezek*, that's the רבנן׳ס שיטה *Rabbanan's shita*.
So it's a מחלוקת *machloket* between סומכוס *Sumchos* and רבנן *Rabbanan*, but
the point whether you pay full נזק *nezek* or half נזק *nezek*,
but the point is you still are responsible for it. So קול
*kol*, that is a sound, if your animal makes a sound that
causes damage to something just by the transfer of sound, that's enough
to be considered חייב chayav, *chayav* for נזיקין *nezikin*. So why with
the slave is it not enough reason for the slave to go
free? And now let's note, there's a difference between causing damage and
performing an injury, that is, damaging someone's property is perhaps different than
the kind of violation that results in the slave's freedom. Actually actively
injuring the slave in a very physical way is perhaps more in
line with what the תורה *Torah* is talking about, but let's see
what it says here. אמר ליה *amar leih*, שאני אדם דכיון דבר
דעת הוא איהו מבעית נפשיה *shani adam dekivan debar daat hu ihu
miv'it nafsheih*.
So a person is different, that is, when a person is injured
rather than a כלי *kli*, because a person who is a בר
דעת *bar daat* somehow even the victim is somehow involved in the
act of being injured. Not exactly sure how to characterize the victim's
role in being blinded or making a loud noise next to someone's
ear and they become deaf being different than making a loud noise
next to someone's glass and the glass breaks. Not exactly sure how
to distinguish, but the point is that somehow the person's active awareness,
being a בר דעת *bar daat*, is enough of a reason to
say that this person bears some responsibility for the resultant injury. Somehow,
it's somehow—I can't say active because the slave was not active in
his own going deaf, but somehow it's less physical and more—I don't
even know exactly the right word. Altercation of some sort, it takes
two to tango, somehow in some minimal way, not to have legal
force, enough to make it so that it's not enough for the
slave to go free from that kind of injury. Right, well, that's
what I was trying to say before, that maybe because it's not
a physical contact injury, that it's less about getting in a fight,
it's less about hurting the person and was more, and that's the
difference between וסמאה *usam'ah* or וחרשה *vechershah* compared to אינו רואה *eino
ro'eh*, אינו שומע *eino shome'a*, that the loss of ability to see
or ability to hear is somehow less than the active injury to
the physical body. It's like somewhat psychological almost. Maybe it's psychological. I
don't know, it's tricky to try to pin down. If you shine
a very bright or if someone in that situation where they hear
an incredibly loud noise, it can cause them to go deaf, it's
not psychological, it's physical. Okay, but the רש״י *Rashi* says like it's
like they're held responsible for their choice of being so afraid or
something, right? It's not about them being there, like they could have
left the room in some sense or something, right? I don't know,
you have to parse how the victim was in somehow involved, right,
somehow, right, yeah, yeah, such that it has he bears some responsibility.
It's also just to note, right, the fact that it is being
distinguished from a כלי *kli*, right, so that's obviously in some sense
more human, right, that's the thing, a human is a בר דעת
*bar daat* and a human being has a different kind of standing
in הלכה *halacha* than כלים *kelim*. So this is similar, okay, כדתניא
*kidtanya*, המבעית חברו פטור patur, מדיני אדם וחייב *hamav'it chavero patur midinei
adam vechayav*. בדיני שמיים. So the same kind of a case where
you injure someone sort of by somehow the sound waves. כיצד: keitzad:
תקע taka באזנו be'ozno והחרשו, vechersho, if you blow in someone's ear
and make him go deaf, פטור, אחזו achazo ותקע באזנו be'ozno והחרשו
vechersho חייב, chayav. but if you hold on to him and blow
into his ear and he becomes deaf, then you're חייב. That is
תקע taka means תקע taka like to blow, like like to make
a loud noise. תקע? taka? Oh, got it. Okay, yeah. So תנו
רבנן: tanu rabanan: הכהו hikehu על עינו al eino וכהתה vechihahta על
שינו... al shino... let's stop here actually because the next part is
going to go into some other stuff that goes towards the next
דף daf and we already did quite a lot today. So.